<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James Issac</title>
    <link>https://jamesis.me/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jamesis.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>James Issac</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020 James Issac</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 22:21:31 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jamesis.me/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>James Issac</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keep Your Eyes Where You Want to Go, and Other Life Lessons I&#39;ve Learned from Motorcycling</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/moto/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 22:21:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/moto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Look through the curve!&amp;rdquo; the instructor barked over the noise of motorcycle engines. I revved the throttle and looked ahead as I blazed past the cones. Here I was, clinging on for dear life and trying to pass the road test.  Was I going too fast? I glanced down at the speedometer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 mph&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything&amp;rsquo;s faster on a motorcycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I learned how to ride. As I look back on those early days when motorcycling seemed so unfamiliar and scary, I appreciate the small steps that have made me a more confident and seasoned rider. And as a firm believer in the value of connecting the dots and learning from different experiences, here are some life lessons that motorcycling has taught me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-trained&#34;&gt;Get Trained&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I rode off into any sunsets, I needed to know how to operate a motorcycle. Taking the Motorcycle Safety Foundation (MSF) course was essential in starting my journey; here I was able to practice on loaner bikes and have watchful eyes monitor my progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, when starting any new endeavor, it&amp;rsquo;s important to learn the correct things. My buddy Mark likes to say, &amp;ldquo;It ain&amp;rsquo;t what you don&amp;rsquo;t know that gets you into trouble. It&amp;rsquo;s what you know for sure that just ain&amp;rsquo;t so&amp;rdquo;. Getting taught by great teachers and mentors, whether they be people (dead or alive), books, courses, etc. is essential to make sure you unlearn any prior misconceptions and have a solid foundation upon which to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s something you&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to learn or get good at? Have you spent time and money to get trained? (And if you&amp;rsquo;re contemplating joining a biker gang, I highly suggest you take the MSF course first.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-well-equipped&#34;&gt;Get Well-Equipped&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;ATGATT: All The Gear All The Time&amp;rdquo;. This is a mantra that wise motorcyclists recite before mounting their steely steeds. And wisely so. There is inherent risk in motorcycling. No metal cage protects you (consequently, car riders are referred to as &amp;lsquo;cagers&amp;rsquo; in the motorcycle community). Enter helmet, armored leather jacket, gloves, and sturdy boots. Sure, I may look like a Power Ranger when I ride, but then again, I&amp;rsquo;ve worked hard to cultivate my well-moisturized skin and chiseled physique. Being properly outfitted helps me concentrate and enjoy the riding experience that much more, knowing that I&amp;rsquo;m doing my best to ride safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in whatever you do, whether it&amp;rsquo;s learning to play the guitar or to paint, having the right tools makes the entire experience more enjoyable. Buying a cheap guitar that has terrible intonation will only add to your frustrations as you begin. Having high quality brushes might not make you the next van Gogh, but it will certainly keep your mind focused on what matters most - creating good paintings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-a-support-circle&#34;&gt;Have a Support Circle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something about motorcycles - the associated thrill and independence, the link between man and machine - captures my attention. On the road, it’s just you and your bike. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve also learned that motorcycling is a very tribe-based experience. There&amp;rsquo;s even something called the Secret Motorcycle Wave (SMW): whenever oncoming bikers pass each other on the road, they flash a salute of sorts, a casual-cool wave that signifies, &amp;lsquo;Hey bruh (or sis), I identify with you&amp;rsquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a fascinating feeling, flashing the SMW to my brothers and sisters as I ride, my heart swelling with camaraderie-induced pride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, friends have been essential in my riding experience. My riding friends helped me overcome my initial fears and challenged me to not become satisfied riding down the same old roads. Good friends inspire you to try and accomplish things you never thought you could do. Find people like that and befriend them (likewise, strive to become an encouraging friend). Your life will become fuller as you share memorable experiences in community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;achieve-small-victories&#34;&gt;Achieve Small Victories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently biked around Lake St. Claire, traveling from Michigan to Canada on my longest motorcycle trip yet. For me, that was a milestone - a culmination of the small victories I&amp;rsquo;d achieved like graduating past practicing in the parking lot, getting comfortable with road and highway speeds, learning to take corners safely, and internalizing the principles I&amp;rsquo;d learned in the MSF course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long ago, the philosopher Lao Tzu philosophized, &amp;ldquo;The journey of a thousand miles begins with a single step.&amp;rdquo; Sometimes I unduly focus on the distance separating me from a goal and I forget to appreciate the steps I&amp;rsquo;ve already taken. And in a culture where mostly big victories are celebrated, perhaps we should be more kind to ourselves and learn to give thanks for the small wins. Being mindful of keeping one foot in front of the other while staying aware of the bigger vision is something I&amp;rsquo;m trying to improve at, which brings me to the final point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;keep-your-eyes-where-you-want-to-go&#34;&gt;Keep Your Eyes Where You Want to Go&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a motorcycle, your eyes are one of your most valuable assets. Where you look is where you go. The flip side to that is called target fixation: the tendency to focus so much attention on an object that you increase your risk of colliding with it. The solution to target fixation is to widen your perspective and look further ahead. By broadening your viewing area, the slower things seem to move, allowing you to be aware of more potential hazards and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the time to write down what you really want out of life is important. Being mindful of your aspirations in different life areas relating to your body, emotions, relationships, finances, and spirituality will help you steer your time and energy wisely. I encourage you to write them out, as the very act of writing and seeing your goals with your eyes is like taking that first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a motorcycle and in life, your body naturally wants to go in the direction you are looking. So where are you focusing your gaze? Remember, where you look is where you go. I wish you a safe and exciting journey.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnífico Ecuador</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/ecuador/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2015 22:21:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/ecuador/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hola! Ecuador es un pais magnifico! I went backpacking with my friends and experienced the sights and culture of Ecuador. Check out the video below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vH_ZHe8lX0M&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>White Water Rafting</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/rafting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2014 22:21:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/rafting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some friends and I went rafting on the Lower New River Gorge and Upper New River Canyon. Got some zip-lining and disc golf in as well. Check out the video I made below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5hV_qh06Tjc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niagara: Untamable Beauty</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/niagara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/niagara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had always heard about the Falls. But like so many before me, I truly understood the Falls only by standing right next to the crashing waters, its majestic roar and unbridled power engulfing my senses. As I stood there, water splashing over me and mist covering my body, I couldn’t help but close my eyes and simply allow myself to be overwhelmed. Water. So tame when coming out of the faucet into my hands. So fierce and uncontainable here in this moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;rainbow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;nia2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I look back, the two words that Niagara invoke are: beauty and power. Sunbeams reflecting off the mist produce glistening rainbows (and yes, even double rainbows) over the waters. Niagara is a very sensory experience. Sight. Sound. Touch. Close your eyes and you hear the roar of thousands of lions. Open them and you see the wonderful handiwork of receding glaciers from ages past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder what the first humans to stumble upon the mighty Falls felt. Their response must have been similar to mine: silent awe. Granted, Niagara is much more commercialized now. However, take away everything except the rushing waters and it’s hard to imagine even the most jaded person having any other response. Niagara has that special ‘something’. And this ‘something’ plucks at my heartstrings. A yearning for adventure, for a land far, far away, for things I can’t quite articulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps that’s what beauty does to you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It renders you speechless.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;niagara2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;nia3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tulip-Time!</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/tulips/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/tulips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Springtime!&lt;/strong&gt; This past winter was one of the most brutal winters in the history of Michigan winters.  It was a winter inside a winter. Fortunately, even unending winters eventually come to an end. So you can imagine my delight when the first blades of grass began poking their green, hopeful heads out into the world above. A frostbitten land was in desperate need of warmth and color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year in Holland, MI millions of tulips burst forth in bloom. In perfect time, the tulips unfurl their petals as if to tell the world, “Hold on, there is still a hope left in this barren land. Spring is here!” And so it was with hopeful hearts that some friends and I trekked out to Holland, eager to see the storied tulip town. Holland has a rich Dutch heritage and the streets were filled with people in traditional Dutch garb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We walked around the Marktplaatz, a 19th-century styled marketplace filled with vendors sharing crafts and selling Dutch food. There was a shoemaker demonstrating the construction of wooden clogs, the traditional Dutch footwear. We walked around the quaint town imagining how life must have been like in the Netherlands so many long years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to top it all off, we ate street-side fried funnel cake, fried Oreos, fried cheesecake, and fried snickers (though I somewhat doubt such delicacies were available back then). Yes, it was a great day to be healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the real stars of the day were of course, the tulips. Arrayed in numerous sizes and colors like an army of multicolored soldiers, the tulips swayed in the gentle afternoon breeze. The looked cool and they knew it. Such confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;strong&gt;when I grow up I want to exude confidence and hope like those tulips.&lt;/strong&gt; Worthy life goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;lighthouse.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;tulips2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC: Lights, People, Action</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/nyc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What can I say about New York City that hasn’t already been said? These lights will make you feel brand new, these streets will inspire you. You get the drift. This is a city filled with movement and magic. I knew all this in my head, but actually going there and basking under the glow of a million LEDs in Times Square opened my eyes. I have gone from darkness into light. Bright, beautiful light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;times-square.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;nyc1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the people: wave after wave of tourists, native New Yorker’s, dreamers, wanderers, celebrities, bottom-dwellers, and everyone in between. I felt energized amidst this constant throb of people and their energy. At the same time, I realized how easy it is to feel alone in a crowd. People are so engrossed in their own lives and calendars that everything else blurs, becoming a casualty of their busyness. Granted, we all get caught up and blinded by our own agendas, but in New York, everything is amplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;street-musician.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;nyc2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of amplification, there are so many good musicians here in NYC! Subway musicians who can give pop-stars music lessons sing their mellifluous tunes to whoever might lend a ear (and a few dollars). I love that about cities: there’s so much talent just waiting to be found. Who knows, that girl sitting next to you on the subway might be an accomplished Broadway singer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;central-park.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;nyc3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite experiences in the city was biking around Central Park. Now, Central Park is like an oasis in the middle of a desert. Juxtaposed between the concrete jungle and rising skyscrapers are trees and lakes. Here, time slows down, if only for a moment; it’s a stark contrast to the hubbub of Times Square. There are people napping, strolling, biking, and just plain relaxing. The weather was perfect, with the sun shining gently and a gentle breeze whispering softly. Basking in the glorious outdoors while riding in the wind and seeing the city’s outline peek through the trees was a surreal experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I must seem like a NYC fanboy by now; the city certainly lured me in with its siren song. Give it a try and experience it for yourself. This city might very well surprise and inspire you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;manhattan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;nyc4&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DC: The Cherry Blossom Festival</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/dc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/dc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1912, Mayor Yukio Ozaki of Tokyo gifted 3,000 cherry trees to the city of Washington, DC as a sign of friendship between the US and Japan. Today, the National Cherry Blossom Festival attracts more than a million people each year who come from all over the world to admire the flowering cherry trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of this amazing history, a few friends and I decided to travel to DC and experience the cherry blossom bloom first-hand. It was packed! I’ve visited DC before, but this time, the city was overflowing with people. We had to wait over an hour just to get a sandwich from a food-truck. But being able to share this moment with so many people as we all enjoyed the blooming trees was surreal. My favorite part was watching the sun set over the Potomac River (pictured above), its golden beams dancing in between the blossoming cherry trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you respond when you encounter beauty in something as simple as a flowering tree? Perhaps all you can do is simply be in awe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Japan for this beautiful, living memorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;dc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;dc&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh: City of Bridges</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spontaneous road trips are sometimes needed to jolt one out of the rhythm of the regular work week. So one weekend, that’s what some friends and I decided to do: travel to Pittsburgh on a whim. We left Michigan on Friday night after work, ate Potbelly sandwiches in the car, and slept all the way to Pittsburg. Well, only the passengers slept, thankfully. I had gotten a rough itinerary of fun things to do from my friend who studied at Carnegie Mellon and our dear friend Google had also given helpful suggestions, so we were set. As a side bonus, the majority of the movie ‘The Dark Knight Rises’ was filmed in Pittsburgh, so I was excited to see the city firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our day started on Saturday. We visited the Strip District, a one-half square mile area filled with street vendors and open-air farmers markets. After stuffing our faces at Pamela’s Diner we waddled around for a bit before setting out to take in the sites of the city. We explored the University of Pittsburgh and its historic looking buildings, napped in the Cathedral of Learning (knowledge transfer by diffusion anyone?), and looked over the city from Mount Washington (pictured above). It had been overcast the whole day and started raining in the evening. Something about rainy days calls for Thai food, so we looked on Yelp, found the restaurant Smiling Banana Leaf and satisfied our cravings. The rest of the night was spent hanging out and playing various board games in our hotel room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving back on Sunday afternoon, I started thinking about the trip. It’s so interesting to see people live out their lives in a different part of the country. It takes you out of your bubble, out of your mundane routine, out into the lives of other people. Perhaps that’s why I enjoy going to new places: life isn’t just about me, even though I so often think it is. Life is about people and relationships. Life is about living in vibrant color with new experiences and discovery. Life is about bridging the gap between who you are and who you want to be. Alright, I’ll stop with the cheesy (genius?) sayings. Go take a spontaneous trip. Peace!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Fall</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/skiing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/skiing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first time I went skiing was at Mt. Brighton (pictured above). Now, seasoned skiers might chuckle at these rounded slopes, but for a first-timer like me, these hills looked like the Himalayan peaks. And indeed, although I had watched countless YouTube videos about skiing the week before, the moment I buckled up the rented boots to the skis, my meticulous research and mental preparation melted away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I signed up for beginners lessons with my group and after learning the basics we proceeded to conquer the beginner bunny slope. To get up this slope there was something called the ‘magic carpet’, which is an automated conveyor belt carrying skiers to the top. I lined up behind the jockeying 5-year-olds and waited. This was it. I closed my eyes and imagined the view from atop the bunny hill. I opened my eyes just in time to see that I was next in line. Too bad I slid onto the magic carpet, lost my balance, and saw the laughing blue sky above me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, after such an accomplishment, how could I quit? And indeed, I learned how to fall a thousand different ways that day. After several hours, I graduated to some of the more difficult slopes. I think I just needed to get used to the fact that I was traveling fast - to get over my fear of this unfamiliar experience. And though I fell in the silliest of ways, each fall prompted me to ask myself &amp;ldquo;What can I do differently?&amp;quot;. After all, according to my buddy T. Edison, “I have not failed. I’ve just found 10,000 ways that won’t work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, in the spirit of discovery and trying new things, here are four lessons I&amp;rsquo;m learning about growing from experiences and not fearing failure. Hopefully you can also apply these to your life and business:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-fear-is-a-friend-whos-misunderstood&#34;&gt;1. Fear is a Friend Who&amp;rsquo;s Misunderstood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the song &amp;lsquo;Heart of Life&amp;rsquo;, John Mayer sings the lyric above. While fear often debilitates, perhaps shifting our perspective on fear changes it from an enemy to a &amp;lsquo;friend&amp;rsquo;? So often we spend our lives running away from fear. What if we instead slowed down to understand what fear is revealing about ourselves? Fear of going fast on the slopes stopped me from going further. The shift in perspective -making speed my friend - allowed me to change my mindset and tweak my technique. It was then that I started enjoying the experience and achieving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about it from a life perspective as well. What fears are subconsciously, yet deliberately causing you to fall or keeping you from moving forward? Realizing that will enable you to experience life adventurously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-try-new-experiences&#34;&gt;2. Try New Experiences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth comes from progress and progress comes from trying new things. Fear often confines us to the familiar. After all, you may ask, if you&amp;rsquo;ve been successful in one area, why risk losing a good thing by branching out? Therein lies the subtle error. Living life solely in maintenance mode robs us of our inherent creativity. Trying something different, whether it be learning an instrument, starting a new business venture, or even drinking green tea instead of the usual morning coffee resets our penchant for familiarity. The reason I decided to try skiing was to learn a new skill. In doing so I made new friends and learned so much about myself. And that&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of being adventurous. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t require scaling Mt. Everest or colonizing Mars, noble pursuits as those are, to feel accomplished. Simply being willing to wander outside the picket fence starts us on a journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-embrace-failure&#34;&gt;3. Embrace Failure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failing is hard. Failing hurts. Falling hurts too. If you follow steps 1 and 2 above, you will get yourself into situations where you&amp;rsquo;re uncomfortable. But that&amp;rsquo;s OK! When I&amp;rsquo;d fallen for the umpteenth time, unable to distinguish between the wet snow on my face from the tears of frustration, I was really tempted to take off my ski gear and head to the warmth of the lodge. But looking back on the experience, I&amp;rsquo;m glad I didn&amp;rsquo;t. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that how life is? In the moment, embracing failure sounds so repugnant. But I&amp;rsquo;m not saying wallow in your mistakes; rather, learn from them. When you&amp;rsquo;re at your lowest, when your feelings condemn you, when frustrations outnumber the hairs on your head, when you&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by thoughts of insufficiency, take time to sit in silence. This moment is crucial: how you respond when you&amp;rsquo;re down determines the kind of person you are becoming. Write down your thoughts, the positive and the negative. What you do next will determine your success, which brings us to the final point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-ask-the-right-questions&#34;&gt;4. Ask the Right Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of your questions determines the quality of your answers. Ask and you will receive. Instead of fostering an internal dialogue of &amp;ldquo;How come I always fail?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Why do bad things happen to me?&amp;rdquo; which only result in negative internal answers like, &amp;ldquo;Because you&amp;rsquo;re a failure!&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re just an unlucky loser&amp;rdquo;, we must cultivate the habit of asking empowering questions. Questions like &amp;ldquo;What can I learn from this experience?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;How can I break this problem into doable steps?&amp;rdquo; re-focus our attention on solutions. In times of failure, I&amp;rsquo;m often my own worst critic. Instead of getting caught in an endless feedback loop of self-pity, I find that re-framing the problem as a question gets me thinking in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you start ideating empowering answers, act on them. It&amp;rsquo;s the momentum generated from positive action, no matter how small, that propels you towards success. And if the recent popularity of the game Flappy Birds has taught me anything, it’s that sometimes, in order to go further, we must learn how to fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;flappy-bird.png&#34; alt=&#34;flappy&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Stop-Motion Whiteboard Animation</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/stop_motion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:31:33 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/stop_motion/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gSDINr23mwI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my friend Aiswarya told me about a video contest held by the National Academy of Engineering in commemoration of their 50th anniversary, I knew I had to do it. The goal was to make a video highlighting engineering innovations and how they enhance quality of life and serve society. Only problem was, the deadline was a week away (since we discovered the contest late). But I’ve always been interested in making videos, so I accepted the challenge. I had previously seen whiteboard animations on YouTube and wanted to try my hand at it, so I decided on the medium for the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the theme, I wanted to show how technology has helped people connect over the years. From the typewriter to the computer to cell phones and apps to the growing potential of virtual/augmented reality, great technology always bridges the gap between people — allowing us to empathize with each other. After all, I think one of a person’s deepest desires is not so much to be fixed as it is to be understood. So I wanted to capture the connection and closeness that technology allows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already had a whiteboard, markers, and camera. I borrowed a tripod from my friend Tianbo and completed my setup (pictured above). So on a Wednesday (March 26th) evening I started, hoping I could finish by the Monday (March 31st ) deadline. I whispered a prayer for drawing skills and creativity, took a black dry-erase marker in hand, and started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drawing and photography took till the end of Saturday (I now sympathize with and greatly admire the animators who breathed life into my favorite classic Disney animations). Then I needed to work on the soundtrack. I took my guitalele and looped 4 chords into the recording software. I timed the music tempo to match the video frame rate and started adding other sonic layers to the soundtrack. Music comes easier to me than drawing, so I was able to finish the soundtrack on Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it was time to edit the pictures and make the video. Since I didn’t have Lightroom to batch edit,I had to edit the pictures individually in Photoshop (next time I will definitely not do that!). But time was scarce and this had to be done, so I created some shortcuts in Photoshop to make editing easier and got to work. A couple of hours later, I was done (albeit bleary-eyed and exhausted). I sent the video to my friends for a final look-through and passed out. I submitted the video on Monday evening; what a satisfying feeling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing this video was an exercise in endurance; by the grace of God I was able to finish in time with a video I’m proud of. Having time to spend on the project only after work and on the weekend meant I had to be efficient. Since I had never done anything like this before, I didn’t know if it was possible to complete a stop-motion video in less than a week. But sometimes, not knowing the line between ‘possible’ and ‘not possible’ helps you attempt and do the impossible. At least that’s how I felt after finishing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ani_setup.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;animation setup&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
