<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James Issac</title>
    <link>https://jamesis.me/authors/james-issac/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jamesis.me/authors/james-issac/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>James Issac</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020 James Issac</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:02:31 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Fall</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/skiing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/skiing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first time I went skiing was at Mt. Brighton (pictured above). Now, seasoned skiers might chuckle at these rounded slopes, but for a first-timer like me, these hills looked like the Himalayan peaks. And indeed, although I had watched countless YouTube videos about skiing the week before, the moment I buckled up the rented boots to the skis, my meticulous research and mental preparation melted away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I signed up for beginners lessons with my group and after learning the basics we proceeded to conquer the beginner bunny slope. To get up this slope there was something called the ‘magic carpet’, which is an automated conveyor belt carrying skiers to the top. I lined up behind the jockeying 5-year-olds and waited. This was it. I closed my eyes and imagined the view from atop the bunny hill. I opened my eyes just in time to see that I was next in line. Too bad I slid onto the magic carpet, lost my balance, and saw the laughing blue sky above me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, after such an accomplishment, how could I quit? And indeed, I learned how to fall a thousand different ways that day. After several hours, I graduated to some of the more difficult slopes. I think I just needed to get used to the fact that I was traveling fast - to get over my fear of this unfamiliar experience. And though I fell in the silliest of ways, each fall prompted me to ask myself &amp;ldquo;What can I do differently?&amp;quot;. After all, according to my buddy T. Edison, “I have not failed. I’ve just found 10,000 ways that won’t work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, in the spirit of discovery and trying new things, here are four lessons I&amp;rsquo;m learning about growing from experiences and not fearing failure. Hopefully you can also apply these to your life and business:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-fear-is-a-friend-whos-misunderstood&#34;&gt;1. Fear is a Friend Who&amp;rsquo;s Misunderstood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the song &amp;lsquo;Heart of Life&amp;rsquo;, John Mayer sings the lyric above. While fear often debilitates, perhaps shifting our perspective on fear changes it from an enemy to a &amp;lsquo;friend&amp;rsquo;? So often we spend our lives running away from fear. What if we instead slowed down to understand what fear is revealing about ourselves? Fear of going fast on the slopes stopped me from going further. The shift in perspective -making speed my friend - allowed me to change my mindset and tweak my technique. It was then that I started enjoying the experience and achieving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about it from a life perspective as well. What fears are subconsciously, yet deliberately causing you to fall or keeping you from moving forward? Realizing that will enable you to experience life adventurously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-try-new-experiences&#34;&gt;2. Try New Experiences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth comes from progress and progress comes from trying new things. Fear often confines us to the familiar. After all, you may ask, if you&amp;rsquo;ve been successful in one area, why risk losing a good thing by branching out? Therein lies the subtle error. Living life solely in maintenance mode robs us of our inherent creativity. Trying something different, whether it be learning an instrument, starting a new business venture, or even drinking green tea instead of the usual morning coffee resets our penchant for familiarity. The reason I decided to try skiing was to learn a new skill. In doing so I made new friends and learned so much about myself. And that&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of being adventurous. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t require scaling Mt. Everest or colonizing Mars, noble pursuits as those are, to feel accomplished. Simply being willing to wander outside the picket fence starts us on a journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-embrace-failure&#34;&gt;3. Embrace Failure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failing is hard. Failing hurts. Falling hurts too. If you follow steps 1 and 2 above, you will get yourself into situations where you&amp;rsquo;re uncomfortable. But that&amp;rsquo;s OK! When I&amp;rsquo;d fallen for the umpteenth time, unable to distinguish between the wet snow on my face from the tears of frustration, I was really tempted to take off my ski gear and head to the warmth of the lodge. But looking back on the experience, I&amp;rsquo;m glad I didn&amp;rsquo;t. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that how life is? In the moment, embracing failure sounds so repugnant. But I&amp;rsquo;m not saying wallow in your mistakes; rather, learn from them. When you&amp;rsquo;re at your lowest, when your feelings condemn you, when frustrations outnumber the hairs on your head, when you&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by thoughts of insufficiency, take time to sit in silence. This moment is crucial: how you respond when you&amp;rsquo;re down determines the kind of person you are becoming. Write down your thoughts, the positive and the negative. What you do next will determine your success, which brings us to the final point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-ask-the-right-questions&#34;&gt;4. Ask the Right Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of your questions determines the quality of your answers. Ask and you will receive. Instead of fostering an internal dialogue of &amp;ldquo;How come I always fail?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Why do bad things happen to me?&amp;rdquo; which only result in negative internal answers like, &amp;ldquo;Because you&amp;rsquo;re a failure!&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re just an unlucky loser&amp;rdquo;, we must cultivate the habit of asking empowering questions. Questions like &amp;ldquo;What can I learn from this experience?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;How can I break this problem into doable steps?&amp;rdquo; re-focus our attention on solutions. In times of failure, I&amp;rsquo;m often my own worst critic. Instead of getting caught in an endless feedback loop of self-pity, I find that re-framing the problem as a question gets me thinking in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you start ideating empowering answers, act on them. It&amp;rsquo;s the momentum generated from positive action, no matter how small, that propels you towards success. And if the recent popularity of the game Flappy Birds has taught me anything, it’s that sometimes, in order to go further, we must learn how to fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;flappy-bird.png&#34; alt=&#34;flappy&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
