<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on James Issac</title>
    <link>https://jamesis.me/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on James Issac</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 21:02:31 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesis.me/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Niagara: Untamable Beauty</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/niagara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/niagara/</guid>
      <description>I had always heard about the Falls. But like so many before me, I truly understood the Falls only by standing right next to the crashing waters, its majestic roar and unbridled power engulfing my senses. As I stood there, water splashing over me and mist covering my body, I couldn’t help but close my eyes and simply allow myself to be overwhelmed. Water. So tame when coming out of the faucet into my hands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tulip-Time!</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/tulips/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/tulips/</guid>
      <description>Springtime! This past winter was one of the most brutal winters in the history of Michigan winters. It was a winter inside a winter. Fortunately, even unending winters eventually come to an end. So you can imagine my delight when the first blades of grass began poking their green, hopeful heads out into the world above. A frostbitten land was in desperate need of warmth and color.
Every year in Holland, MI millions of tulips burst forth in bloom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC: Lights, People, Action</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/nyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/nyc/</guid>
      <description>What can I say about New York City that hasn’t already been said? These lights will make you feel brand new, these streets will inspire you. You get the drift. This is a city filled with movement and magic. I knew all this in my head, but actually going there and basking under the glow of a million LEDs in Times Square opened my eyes. I have gone from darkness into light.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DC: The Cherry Blossom Festival</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/dc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/dc/</guid>
      <description>In 1912, Mayor Yukio Ozaki of Tokyo gifted 3,000 cherry trees to the city of Washington, DC as a sign of friendship between the US and Japan. Today, the National Cherry Blossom Festival attracts more than a million people each year who come from all over the world to admire the flowering cherry trees.
In light of this amazing history, a few friends and I decided to travel to DC and experience the cherry blossom bloom first-hand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh: City of Bridges</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>Spontaneous road trips are sometimes needed to jolt one out of the rhythm of the regular work week. So one weekend, that’s what some friends and I decided to do: travel to Pittsburgh on a whim. We left Michigan on Friday night after work, ate Potbelly sandwiches in the car, and slept all the way to Pittsburg. Well, only the passengers slept, thankfully. I had gotten a rough itinerary of fun things to do from my friend who studied at Carnegie Mellon and our dear friend Google had also given helpful suggestions, so we were set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Fall</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/first-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:02:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/first-blog/</guid>
      <description>I went skiing for the first time at Mt. Brighton (pictured above). Now seasoned skiers might chuckle at these rounded slopes, but for a first-timer like me, these hills looked like the Himalayan peaks. And indeed, although I had watched countless YouTube videos about skiing the week before, the moment I buckled up the rented boots to the skis, my meticulous research and mental preparation melted away.
I signed up for beginners lessons with my group, and after learning the basics, we proceeded to ski down the beginner bunny slope.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>