<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>photography | James Issac</title>
    <link>https://jamesis.me/tags/photography/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jamesis.me/tags/photography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>photography</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020 James Issac</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:31:33 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jamesis.me/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>photography</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/tags/photography/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Stop-Motion Whiteboard Animation</title>
      <link>https://jamesis.me/post/stop_motion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:31:33 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jamesis.me/post/stop_motion/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gSDINr23mwI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my friend Aiswarya told me about a video contest held by the National Academy of Engineering in commemoration of their 50th anniversary, I knew I had to do it. The goal was to make a video highlighting engineering innovations and how they enhance quality of life and serve society. Only problem was, the deadline was a week away (since we discovered the contest late). But I’ve always been interested in making videos, so I accepted the challenge. I had previously seen whiteboard animations on YouTube and wanted to try my hand at it, so I decided on the medium for the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the theme, I wanted to show how technology has helped people connect over the years. From the typewriter to the computer to cell phones and apps to the growing potential of virtual/augmented reality, great technology always bridges the gap between people — allowing us to empathize with each other. After all, I think one of a person’s deepest desires is not so much to be fixed as it is to be understood. So I wanted to capture the connection and closeness that technology allows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already had a whiteboard, markers, and camera. I borrowed a tripod from my friend Tianbo and completed my setup (pictured above). So on a Wednesday (March 26th) evening I started, hoping I could finish by the Monday (March 31st ) deadline. I whispered a prayer for drawing skills and creativity, took a black dry-erase marker in hand, and started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drawing and photography took till the end of Saturday (I now sympathize with and greatly admire the animators who breathed life into my favorite classic Disney animations). Then I needed to work on the soundtrack. I took my guitalele and looped 4 chords into the recording software. I timed the music tempo to match the video frame rate and started adding other sonic layers to the soundtrack. Music comes easier to me than drawing, so I was able to finish the soundtrack on Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it was time to edit the pictures and make the video. Since I didn’t have Lightroom to batch edit,I had to edit the pictures individually in Photoshop (next time I will definitely not do that!). But time was scarce and this had to be done, so I created some shortcuts in Photoshop to make editing easier and got to work. A couple of hours later, I was done (albeit bleary-eyed and exhausted). I sent the video to my friends for a final look-through and passed out. I submitted the video on Monday evening; what a satisfying feeling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing this video was an exercise in endurance; by the grace of God I was able to finish in time with a video I’m proud of. Having time to spend on the project only after work and on the weekend meant I had to be efficient. Since I had never done anything like this before, I didn’t know if it was possible to complete a stop-motion video in less than a week. But sometimes, not knowing the line between ‘possible’ and ‘not possible’ helps you attempt and do the impossible. At least that’s how I felt after finishing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ani_setup.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;animation setup&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
